The Wandering Earth is a 2019 Chinese sci-fi disaster film
《流浪地球》是一部2019年發行的中國科幻災難電影
Based on the novel of the same name
改編自同名小說
In the film, humanity leaves the dying sun behind
電影中，人類用推動力極大的引擎
Using impossibly powerful thrusters
將地球推離垂死的太陽
Earth is taking its 2000 year long journey
向半人馬座進行2000年的
Towards Alpha Centauri
漫長旅程
It was a huge financial and critical success in China
電影在中國票房和口碑都很成功
While it is absolutely not an all time classic
雖然不是經典之作
It is at least as good as...
它至少可以媲美……
Independence Day
《天煞-地球反擊戰》……？
But for the purpose of this episode
但這一期視頻裡
I want to point out one specific quality of the film
我隻想指出這部電影的其中一點
That despite its ludicrously Hollywood premise and effects
盡管電影表面看來隻是特效大片
Underneath, there is a deeply Chinese story
電影核心卻訴說著一個中國的故事
All good writers write about themselves
優秀的作家寫的都是自己的故事
That's because the goal of a good writer is not to tell stories
那是因為好作家的目標並非講故事
But through stories, evoke certain emotions
而是通過故事，喚起情緒
And emotions are such personal things
而情緒是十分個人的感受
By necessity, all good stories are drawn from the writer's personal experience
因此，所有好故事都來自作家的個人經歷
It's the Lord of the Rings and World War One
例如《魔戒》和第一次世界大戰
Where the Dead Marshes was inspired by the Battle of the Somme
書中的死亡沼澤，靈感來自索姆河之戰
By drawing from the writer's experience
作者通過自己的感受
No matter how fantastical the setting seems
突破了奇幻設定的屏障
Tolkien was able to make the Dead Marshes feel real
將死亡沼澤寫得十分真實
Because the sense of dread was real
因為其背后的恐懼感是真實的
Experienced by Tolkien first hand.
是作者參戰，親身的體驗
Similarly, in The Wandering Earth
同樣，在《流浪地球》中
To create a post-apocalyptic dystopian China
為了描繪一個末日后的中國
The filmmaker draws inspiration from the negative aspects of living in China
電影從中國生活的方方面面中取出了缺點印象
However trivial.
細致入微
For the setting alone
看看世界的背景設定
There are these wet and dark back alleys
這些潮濕和黑暗的后巷
Complete with these LED store signs that are everywhere in China
還有這些中國到處都是的LED看板
And of course, it's credit score and loans
看板寫的是信用評分和貸款
A controversial branch of business, operating in legal grey areas
在中國充滿爭議的一門生意
The tacky red banner plastered with government slogans
俗氣的紅色橫幅貼滿了宣傳口號
The gambling
賭博
The girl dressed like a cheap night club bunny
穿的像夜總會兔女郎的女生
And the pirated video games
和盜版電子游戲
These are all common elements of the Chinese underbelly
這些都是中國陰暗面的元素
In reflection of the human condition
而故事裡
There is the classroom scene
也有教室的場景
Reflecting on the heavily criticized performative education
諷刺了中國重視表演形式的基礎教育
The hostile and unsafe work environment
惡劣又危險的工作環境
With worn out equipment
老舊的設備
Tacky public service announcements that nobody takes seriously
老土，又沒有人聽的口號
Police corruption and misfeasance
警察的貪污和瀆職
Where they take bribes in public
公然受賄
And still don't do their jobs
卻又不盡職責
The state of pornography
還有色情產業
It's illegal in China
色情產品在中國全面違法
So good pornography circulates like currency
於是好的色情物品就像貨幣一樣流通
Enough to be use for bribery
足夠用來賄賂公職人員
Every frame of this movie lives and breathes
這部電影的每一個畫面都散發著中國氣息
It doesn't have to tell you how chaotic and lawless this world is
它無需告訴你世界有多荒亂
Through the iconography that the filmmaker draws from real life
通過從現實生活中汲取的設定
The film evokes an emotion among viewers that feels real and grounded
電影直接地掀起了觀眾的真實情緒
Compare this to L.O.R.D., which was "inspired" by Fate/Stay Night
和“參考”《Fate/stay night》的《爵跡》相比
Or Eragon, inspired by Star Wars and Lord of the Rings
或者是《俠影魔龍》（參考《星戰》和《摩戒》）
The world is nothing but cliches and exposition
兩者的世界都是陳腔濫調
Because those films are trying to tell other people's stories
因為這些電影講的是別人的故事
Instead of telling their experience
而不是分享自己的經驗
Their emotions
自己的情緒
But that's just the art direction
但那些隻是皮毛
We need to go deeper
我們需要更進一步
Because the philosophy behind The Wandering Earth is also a Chinese one.
因為《流浪地球》背后的哲學充滿中國氣息
Stories of humans leaving Earth behind due to catastrophe are not rare
人類因災難離開地球的故事並不罕見
But the mass exodus usually happens on a spaceship
但人類通常是坐著宇宙飛船離開的
I'm going to make a bold generalization here
容我大膽概括
But I think a lot of you would agree These movies draw their philosophy
這些電影的構思
From Noah's ark.
來自諾亞方舟
In the west, when nature is destroyed It's usually unstoppable
在西方，大自然的毀滅往往勢不可擋
Like the wrath of god
如同上帝之怒
Humans live in god's creation
人類生活在上帝創造的世界裡
So when god's creation comes to an end
當世界末日到來
Humanity is at god's mercy
人類隻能等候上帝的憐憫
In Chinese mythology, however
然而，在中國神話中
There is no such supreme being
這樣至高無上的神明並不存在
Humans and gods alike obey the natural order
神仙和人都要遵守自然秩序
The "Tao", if you will.
也就是“道”
So, in Chinese flood myths
所以，在中國的洪水神話裡
The hole in the sky is patched up by a goddess
天破了，就由女神填補
The flood from the Yellow River was contained and drained
黃河泛濫了
By human constructions over the course of 13 long years
人類就花13年時間治理
The Chinese equivalent of the Icarus myth
和西方的伊卡洛斯神話不同
Talks about a man chasing the sun and dies of thirst
中國追逐太陽的夸父盡管渴死了
But he leaves behind a peach forest as a water supply
他卻留下一片桃林
So that future generations may continue the chase
讓后代能追得更遠
In Chinese mythology, and thus, philosophy
因此，在中國的神話以及哲學裡
Nature is malleable
大自然是可塑的
It can be shaped
可以被改變
It can be conquered
可以被征服
It may take generations of effort
盡管需要數代人的努力
But it is possible, and honorable
但是移動整個地球
To move the Earth.
是一件偉大的事
In fact, The Wandering Earth is just a sci-fi retelling of a Chinese legend
事實上，《流浪地球》不過是一個披上了科幻外皮的神話故事
It's a story about a foolish old man
也就是《愚公移山》
And his quest to dig through a pair of mountains
故事裡，愚公一心挖山
For the simple reason of them obstructing his home
隻因兩座大山擋住了家門
When he is told that this is impossible
當旁人質疑他時
That he'll never finish this within his lifetime
當他人說他一輩子都不可能把山移平時
He says
他說
"It's fine"
“沒事”
"We still have our children"
“我們還有孩子”
"And our children have children later"
“孩子的孩子，還有孩子”
Definitely someday
“終有一天”
"The ice will melt"
“冰一定會化成水的”
And with that, we can finally talk about the theme of The Wandering Earth
知道了這些前提后，我們終於可以談論了《流浪地球》的主題了
The core message that makes this story, a Chinese story
《流浪地球》背后的核心思想
The value of home.
是“家”
The question that every single Chinese kid asks
每個孩子聽了《愚公移山》的故事后
When they first hear the mountain moving legend
都會問：
Is "why don't they just move?"
“他們為什麼不搬家？”
And, I only truly learned the answer after I grew up
而我也是長大之后才明白答案
In Chinese, the word for home and family is the same.
在中文裡，Family和Home用的是同一個字
The distinction between the two exists
兩者之間有所區別
But not to the same degree as in North American culture
當相比北美文化，區別是很小的
In the west, we sometimes say "Home is where the family is"
在西方，會有人說 “家人在的地方就是家”
"Asgard is not a place, it's a people"
“聖域界不是一個地方，它是一個民族”
China, however, doesn't share this view.
然而，中國的想法不太相同
With thousands of years of history rooted in agriculture
數千年的農業歷史根深蒂固
The land is just as much a family member, as the people
在這裡，土地也是家庭一員
For Chinese people, the land is the witness of a continuous legacy
對中國人來說，土地就是歷史見証
It's the imprint of history
時光的印記
Thus, when you move
搬家的時候
You leave the history behind
歷史會被留下
And that is unacceptable to the culture that, to this day
這對一個時至今日依然拜祭祖先的民族而言
Still practices ancestor worship
不可接受
Later in the film, humanity faces a dilemma
電影高潮時，人類需要作出重大抉擇
We must choose between recreating human life from scratch on a foreign planet
我們應該在新的星球上重新培養人類
"300,000 human embryos are stored at the space station Navigation Platform,"
“宇航員空間站冷藏了三十萬人類受精卵”
"Along with 100 million seedlings base."
“和1億顆基礎農作的種子。”
Or risk everything trying to keep the Earth in one piece
還是要賭上一切，試圖保住地球
To Chinese culture
對中國文化裡
Home, is part of the civilization
家，是文明的一部分
It cannot be digitized
無法備份
It cannot be restarted
無法重建
It's the reason the foolish old man chooses not to move
這就是愚公不搬家的原因
It's the reason humanity didn't leave Earth on spaceships
這就是人類沒有選擇坐飛船離開地球的原因
Because even if we have to reshape nature
哪怕要重塑大自然
It's worth it, for our home.
為了家園，值得。
Knowing all of these is maybe what makes the film worked for me
了解到背后這些細節，可能就是我喜歡這部電影的原因
Characters make rash, emotional decisions
電影裡的人不完全理智，跟普通人一樣
Like real humans
會做出情緒化的決定
And all their decisions are made surrounding different concepts of home
而它們的抉擇都是圍繞著“家”這個概念
A military team is failing their mission
一支軍隊小隊任務即將失敗
And if carry on, some of them will likely die.
若繼續下去，必有傷亡
So one of them sabotages the entire mission
於是，其中一人選擇毀掉整個任務
To keep the team together
保全小隊所有人
When Earth's destruction seems imminent
當地球的毀滅迫在眉睫時
Some of us would give up hope
會有人選擇放棄希望
And prefer to spend our last moments with our families
寧願在最后時刻與家人相處
"I want to go home"
“我想回家”
"To meet my mother"
“見我媽媽”
When the protagonist's young sister is falling to her death
當主角的妹妹要從高處摔死時
Her brother, without hesitation or even a plan
他的哥哥，不顧一起地
Jumps for her
跟著她跳過去
And the astronaut who sacrifice himself
就連犧牲自己的宇航員
Didn't really do it for the good of humanity
也不是為了人類而犧牲
But for his son
為的是兒子
"Come..."
“來...”
"My son"
“兒子“
I admit, I'm very bias towards this film
我承認，我對這部電影很偏袒
Being an immigrant
作為一個移民
I have been adfried and wandering since I was a teenager
我從少年時期便一直在“流浪”
So this film hits me on a personal level
所以這部電影從心底處打動了我
But, despite its shortcomings
盡管帶著瑕疵
The emotion behind The Wandering Earth rings true
《流浪地球》背后的情感真實
The core message feels authentic
核心思想也發自內心
The fact that the film strides to be more than a blockbuster entertainment
這部電影不甘於成為一部普通的爆米花電影
That alone, is a step above a lot of films
僅此一點，就比很多電影都優秀了